David Rapaport Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
David Rapaport Papers 1911-1997 (bulk 1948-1960)
MSS37325
Rapaport, David
23,500 items
91 containers
43 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychologist and author. Correspondence, drafts of speeches, lectures, and writings, memoranda, reports, legal documents, and printed matter concerning Rapaport's research and writings in the fields of psychology and psychoanalysis and his association with the Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Massachusetts.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bettelheim, Bruno--Correspondence.; Burnham, John C. (John Chynoweth), 1929-2017--Correspondence.; Escalona, Sibylle K. (Sibylle Korsch), 1915- --Correspondence.; Fenichel, Hanna--Correspondence.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Gill, Merton M. (Merton Max), 1914-1994--Correspondence.; Hartmann, Heinz, 1894-1970--Correspondence.; Kubie, Lawrence S. (Lawrence Schlesinger), 1896-1973--Correspondence.; Mayman, Martin--Correspondence.; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990--Correspondence.; Rapaport, David.; Schafer, Roy--Correspondence.; Sterba, Richard F.--Correspondence.; Strasser, Elvira Rapaport. Elvira Rapaport Strasser papers. 1941-1997.; Wolff, Peter H.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Austen Riggs Center.
Subjects
Behaviorism (Psychology); Consciousness.; Ego (Psychology); Emotions.; Kibbutzim.; Memory.; Mental health facilities--Massachusetts--Stockbridge.; Motivation (Psychology); Psychoanalysis.; Psychological tests.; Psychology.; Spiritualism.; Thought and thinking.
Places
Hungary--Social life and customs.; Palestine--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Authors.; Psychologists.
Provenance
The papers of David Rapaport, psychologist and author, were deposited in the Library of Congress by his wife, Elvira Rapaport Strasser, between 1962 and 1997. Strasser and her daughter, Juliet Rapaport Phillips, converted these deposits to gifts between 1962 and 1998. Additional material was given by Phillips in 1976 and 1996 and by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1961 and 1976.
Transfers
Audio recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.separatedmat
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1911, Sept. 30 Born, Munkács, Hungary
1932 Leader in Hashomer Hatzair, a Zionist youth movement Married Elvira Strasser (died 1998)
1933 Graduated with degree in mathematics and experimental physics, Royal Hungarian University, Budapest, Hungary
1933 1935 Worked as a surveyor in a kibbutz in Palestine
1935 1938 Analysand of Imre Hermann
1938 Ph.D. in psychology, Royal Hungarian University, Budapest, Hungary Immigrated to the United States
1939 1940 Staff psychologist, Osawatomie State Hospital, Osawatomie, Kans.
1940 1948 Staff psychologist, research director, and administrator, Menninger Foundation, Topeka, Kans.
1942 Published Emotions and Memory. Baltimore: Williams and Wilkins Co.
1944 1948 Consultant, United States Surgeon General's Committee on Clinical Psychology
1945 1946 Published with Merton Max Gill and Roy Schafer Diagnostic Psychological Testing. Chicago: The Year Book Publishers
1945 1949 Founder and secretary, Division of Clinical and Abnormal Psychology, American Psychological Association
1946 1948 Clinical professor of psychology, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kans. Consultant, Veterans Administration Hospital, Topeka, Kans.
1948 1960 Research associate, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass.
1951 Published Organization and Pathology of Thought. New York: Columbia University Press
1960 Published The Structure of Psychoanalytic Theory: A Systematizing Attempt. New York: International Universities Press
1960, Dec. 14 Died, Stockridge, Mass.
1967 Publication of Collected Papers of David Rapaport, edited by Merton Max Gill. New York: Basic Books
Scope and Content Note
The papers of David Rapaport (1911-1960) span the years 1911-1997, with the bulk of the material dating from 1948 to 1960. The collection documents Rapaport's research and writings in the fields of psychology and psychoanalysis largely as a research associate at the Austen Riggs Center in Stockbridge, Massachusetts. The papers are in English and Hungarian and are organized in two parts. Part I contains material received by the Library between 1962 and 1970 and is arranged in five series: General Correspondence, Foreign Correspondence, Austen Riggs Center, Miscellaneous Correspondence, and Speeches, Writings, and Lectures File. Part II comprises an addition to the collection and is organized in four series: David Rapaport Papers, Elvira Rapaport Strasser Papers, Formerly Closed, and Closed material.
Rapaport's correspondence dates primarily from 1948 to 1960 during his years at the Austen Riggs Center. It focuses on his research and writings in psychology and psychoanalysis including his development of diagnostic psychological testing and his efforts to clarify and systematize psychoanalytic theory. The General Correspondence series contains Rapaport's extensive correspondence with psychologists, psychoanalysts, and professional organizations in the United States. Correspondence with colleagues overseas is located in the Foreign Correspondence series. Prominent correspondents include Bruno Bettelheim, John C. Burnham, Sibylle K. Escalona, Hanna Fenichel, Anna Freud, Merton Max Gill, Heinz Hartmann, Lawrence S. Kubie, Karl A. Menninger, Martin Mayman, Roy Schafer, Richard F. Sterba, and Peter H. Wolff. Routine correspondence including invitations to speak and requests for reprints is filed in the Miscellaneous Correspondence series. The Austen Riggs Center series largely concerns administrative matters pertaining to committees, funding, programs, research associates, staff, and trustees.
The Speeches, Writings, and Lectures File series documents Rapaport's prolific writing career, his extensive teaching experience, and his numerous speaking engagements. Drafts of articles, books, book reviews, lectures, and speeches, transcripts of discussions, correspondence with colleagues, and research material explore his research interests in psychological diagnostic testing, ego psychology, emotions and memory, metapsychology, motivation, psychoanalytic theory, and thought processes.
Part II contains an addition to the Rapaport Papers. Included are photocopies of outgoing letters, largely dated 1950-1960, and a lengthy letter to friends describing a trip to his native Hungary in 1960. Also included are a series of dream notes made by Rapaport as part of his research on consciousness. The addition further includes two of his early psychological works published in Hungary prior to his immigration to the United States.
The bulk of Part II consists of the papers of Rapaport's wife, Elvira Rapaport Strasser, a mathematician and university professor, who resumed use of her maiden name in the early 1970s. Her papers document programs and scholarships established in her husband's name at the Austen Riggs Center and the Hebrew University of Jerusalem. The bulk of her papers was closed until April 2003 and is now available in the Formerly Closed series. Among the formerly closed material is correspondence with her husband's colleagues including Merton Max Gill, exchanges with fellow mathematicians, and letters from Hungarian friends and family members. The Formerly Closed series also contains her unpublished memoirs describing her early life in Hungary, her experiences on a kibbutz in Palestine in 1933-1935, and her immigration to the United States in 1938.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in two parts composed of nine series:
Part I:
General Correspondence, 1948-1960
Foreign Correspondence, 1948-1960
Austen Riggs Center, 1948-1960
Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1938-1960
Speeches, Writings, and Lectures File, 1911-1960
Part II:
David Rapaport Papers, 1936-1993
Elvira Rapaport Strasser Papers, 1941-1997
Formerly Closed, 1934-1996
Closed, 1942
Container List
- Part I: General Correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box I:1-33)
  Correspondence with psychologists, psychoanalysts, and professional organizations.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or organization.
  - Adams-Anderson (Box I:1)
  - Anderson-Bergman (Box I:2)
  - Bergman-Bibring (Box I:3)
  - Bibring-Burnham (Box I:4)
  - Burnham-Cort (Box I:5)
  - Craig-Eissler (Box I:6)
  - Eitingon-Fenichel (Box I:7)
  - Fenichel-Fremont (Box I:8)
  - Freyberg-Gill (Box I:9)
  - Gill-Goldberg (Box I:10)
  - Goldstein-Harms (Box I:11)
  - Hartmann-Holman (Box I:12)
  - Holt (Box I:13)
  - Holzberg-Julay (Box I:14)
  - Kagan-Klein (Box I:15)
  - Klein-Kobler (Box I:16)
  - Koch-Levitt (Box I:17)
  - Levitt-Lustman (Box I:18)
  - McBee-Mendelschen (Box I:19)
  - Menninger Foundation (Box I:20)
  - Menninger Foundation (Box I:21)
  - Mundy-Perry (Box I:22)
  - Pertschonok-Powdermaker (Box I:23)
  - Powers-Reichard (Box I:24)
  - Reider-Romano (Box I:25)
  - Rosenbaum-Schafer (Box I:26)
  - Scheerer-Schwartz (Box I:27)
  - Schwartz-Sharma (Box I:28)
  - Shepard-Stagner (Box I:29)
  - Staiman-Troup (Box I:30)
  - University of California-Western News (Box I:31)
  - Westley-Wolff (Box I:32)
  - Wolff-Zinberg (Box I:33)
- Part I: Foreign Correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box I:34-40)
  Correspondence with foreign psychologists and psychoanalysts.
  Arranged alphabetically by country and therein alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Argentina-England (Box I:34)
  - England-France (Box I:35)
  - France-India (Box I:36)
  - Israel (Box I:37)
    - A-I
    - K-Z (Box I:38)
  - Italy-South Africa (Box I:39)
  - South Africa-Switzerland (Box I:40)
- Part I: Austen Riggs Center, 1948-1960 (Box I:41-44)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, and printed matter concerning administrative matters.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - Activities-Czeisler (Box I:41)
  - Field Foundation-Rapaport (Box I:42)
  - Rapaport-Social Problems Council (Box I:43)
  - Social Problems Council-Trustees (Box I:44)
- Part I: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1938-1960 (Box I:45-46)
  Correspondence of a comparatively brief duration including invitations to speak and requests for reprints.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - A-K (Box I:45)
  - L-Z (Box I:46)
- Part I: Speeches, Writings, and Lectures File, 1911-1960 (Box I:47-76)
  Drafts of articles, book reviews, books, lectures, and speeches, transcripts of discussions and conference proceedings, correspondence, research, and notes.
  Unarranged.
  - "The Theory of Ego Autonomy," 1956 (Box I:47)
  - Letter to Contemporary Psychology, 1957
  - Symposium on Cognition, Boulder, Colo., 1957
  - Discussion of C. E. Osgood's paper, "A Behavioristic Analysis of Perception and Language as Cognitive Phenomena," 1955
  - "Cognition, Cognitive Organizations and Consciousness," 1955
  - Strachey, Alix, correspondence, 1952
  - Questions and answers, (6 folders)
  - Lectures, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, New York, N.Y., 1958 (Box I:48)
  - Lectures, New York Society of Freudian Psychologists, New York, N.Y., 1960
  - "Elementary Metapsychology," 1957, (5 folders)
  - Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., lecture to fellows on metapsychology, 1959
  - "The Conceptual Model of Psychoanalysis," 1951 (Box I:49)
  - Mass Communications Seminar, Viking Fund, New York, N.Y., 1951
  - "Projective Techniques and the Theory of Thinking," 1952
  - "On the Psychoanalytic Theory of Affects," 1952-1953, (2 folders)
  - "Trophy and Triumph," 1939
  - Symposium on the Theory of the Therapeutic Results of Psychoanalysis, 1937
  - "Two Short Supplementary Notes," 1929
  - "The Study of Defense Mechanisms and Its Importance for Psychoanalytic Technique," 1940
  - "Some Remarks on Freud's Place in the History of Science," 1946
  - Review of New Ways in Psychoanalysis by Karen Horney, 1939
  - "Psychoanalysis of Character," 1941
  - "Present Trends in Psychoanalytic Theory and Practice on Masturbation," 1938
  - "Ego Strength and Ego Weakness," 1938
  - "On the Economic Function of Screen-Memories Anorexia," 1945
  - "Brief Psychotherapy Concerning the Anxiety of the Dead," 1922
  - "A Dream Analysis," 1929
  - "Early Stages of Ego Development"
  - "The Economics of Pseudologia Phantastica"
  - Reviews of the Collected Papers of Otto Fenichel, 1954-1955
  - "Shall the Rorschach Method Be Standardized?" 1938 (Box I:50)
  - "Histamine in the Treatment of Psychosis: A Psychiatric and Objective Psychological Study," 1940
  - "Some Considerations in Connection with the Application of Metrazol Shock Treatment in the Psychosis of General Paresis," 1941
  - "Teleology and the Emotions," 1941
  - Emotions and Memory, 1942-1947
  - "The Scatter: Intelligence Testing and Clinical Diagnosis," 1944
  - "Principles Underlying Non-Projective Tests of Personality," 1946
  - "Psychological Testing, Its Practical and Its Heuristic Significance," 1947
  - "Technological Growth and the Psychology of Man," 1949
  - "The Scientific Basis of Clinical Psychology," 1948
  - "In Memoriam: Kurt Lewin," 1947
  - "The Theoretical Implications of Diagnostic Testing Procedures," 1950, (2 folders)
  - "Diagnostic Testing in Psychiatric Practice," 1950
  - Organization and Pathology of Thought
    - Chapter outline, 1951
    - Correspondence, 1950-1953
    - Reviews, 1951-1953
  - "On the Psychoanalytic Theory of Motivation," 1960
  - "On Metapsychology," 1959
  - "An Historical Survey of Psychoanalytic Ego Psychology," 1958 (Box I:51)
  - "Toward a Theory of Thinking," 1951
  - "Paul Schilder's Contribution to the Theory of Thought-Processes," 1951, (2 folders)
  - Josiah Macy Jr. Foundation, Third Conference on Problems of Consciousness, 1952
  - "States of Consciousness: A Psychopathological and Psychodynamic View," 1951, (2 folders)
  - "Problems of Consciousness," review, 1951
  - Medical Psychology reviews, 1953-1954, (4 folders)
  - A History of Experimental Psychology, review, 1950
  - Book reviews, 1939-1945
  - "A Study of Thinking," 1956
  - Energy Structure in Psychoanalysis, review, 1955
  - Personality and Psychotherapy, review, 1950 (Box I:52)
  - The Principles of Psychology, review, 1950
  - The Psychology of Thought and Judgment, review, 1955
  - Personality: In Nature, Society and Culture, review, 1948
  - Psychoanalytic Explorations in Art, review, 1952
  - Learning Theory and Personality Dynamics, review, 1950
  - The Emotions: Outline of a Theory, review, 1948
  - The Psychology of Imagination, review, 1948
  - The Psychology of Thinking, review, 1952
  - Cybernetics, review, 1950
  - H. H. Wieck's Zur Psychologie und Psychopathologie, review, 1955
  - "Scatter in a Battery of Tests," 1940
  - "Concept Formation and Personality Research," 1945
  - "Diagnosing Schizophrenia by Psychological Tests," 1945
  - "Theoretical and Practical Conclusions of a Testing Program Conducted Over Two Years, Including a Battery of Seven Tests," 1945
  - "Tests," Menninger Foundation, 1946
  - "Technological Growth and the Psychology of Man," 1947
  - "The Autonomy of the Ego," 1951
  - "Paul Schilder's Contribution to the Theory of Thought Processes," 1951
  - "Projective Techniques on the Theory of Thinking," 1951
  - "On the Psychoanalytic Theory of Affects," 1953
  - Discussion of C. E. Osgood's paper, 1957
  - "The Study of Kibbutz Education and Its Bearing on the Theory of Development," 1958
  - "An Historical Survey of Psychoanalytic Ego Psychology," 1958 (Box I:53)
  - "Autonomy," 1956, (2 folders)
  - "On Metapsychology," 1959, (6 folders)
  - "The Traditional View of Art," 1951 (Box I:54)
  - Hoaxes
    - Australian hoax, 1952
    - Australian News and Information Bureau, 1952-1953
    - Baker, Sidney J., 1952-1954
    - Harris, Max, 1953
    - Hornadge, W., 1952-1953
    - McAuley, James, 1952-1953
    - The National Press Printing, Melbourne, Australia, 1952
    - Stewart, Harold, 1952-1957, (2 folders)
    - Orpheus, by Harold Stewart
    - Clare, John
    - Picard, Roger, "Literary Artifices and Hoaxes"
    - "Piltdown Man"
    - Radio Times, 1954
    - Toscanini, Arturo, "Tchaikovsky's Fifth"
    - Wolcott, Alexander
    - Wolf boy
    - Pehriad, Kohmar
    - MacDougall, Curtis
    - "The Man Who Never Was"
  - Ficke, Gladys
  - Abraham, Karl
  - Heseltine, Philip
  - Kipling, Rudyard
  - Ficke, Arthur Davison, (2 folders)
  - Bynner, Witter (Box I:55)
  - Harris, Max
  - DuPre, George
  - Kris, Ernst
  - Kris, Ernst, seminar, New Haven, Conn., 1952
  - Hoaxes
  - Wilson, Edmund, review of The Sweeniad, (2 folders)
  - Cassel Hospital, Richmond, England, (5 folders)
  - Bibring, Edward, theory of depression, (3 folders)
  - Report on Vannevar Bush's Science, the Endless Frontier (Box I:56)
  - Research plan for study of amnesia, circa 1943-1944
  - "The Theory of Attention Cathexis," 1959
  - "The Theory of Ego Autonomy," 1958
  - Bergman, Paul, "The Role of Faith in Psychotherapy," 1956
  - Berman, Leo, "Problems in Working Toward an Integration of Individual and Group Psychology," 1956
  - Activity and passivity, (8 folders)
  - Freud's Influence on American Psychology, (5 folders); (3 folders) (Box I:57)
  - "Motivation," 1960, (2 folders); (3 folders) (Box I:58)
  - "Psychoanalysis as a Developmental Psychology", (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box I:59, Box I:60)
  - "States of Consciousness", (3 folders)
  - "Psychoanalytic Theory of Consciousness and a Study of Dreams", (2 folders)
  - Dream seminars, 1953-1956, (21 folders) (Box I:61)
  - Ego psychology seminar, 1951, (9 folders) (Box I:62)
  - "Present-Day Conceptions of the Development and Functions of the Ego," 1953
  - Outline of "Ego Psychology," 1952
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of the Ego," Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1954
  - "A Survey of Psychoanalytic Ego Psychology," Denver, Colo.
  - "Present-Day Psychoanalytic Ego Psychology and Its Clinical Relevance," 1953, (2 folders) (Box I:63)
  - "Clinical Implications of Ego Psychology," 1954
  - "Present-Day Ego Psychology," 1956-1957, (2 folders)
  - Eissler, K. R., "The Effect of the Structure of the Ego on Psychoanalytic Technique," 1952
  - "Outline on the Problem of Emotions"
  - Worcester State Hospital, Worcester, Mass., "The Problem of the Psychological Energy Concept," 1957
  - Ginsburg, Sol
    - "The Role of Work: A Contribution to Psychology," 1953
    - "The Role of Values in Psychotherapy," 1951, (2 folders)
  - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., lectures, 1954, (2 folders)
  - Group theory, 1954, (3 folders) (Box I:64)
  - Piaget, Jean, paper, 1954
  - Hungarian translations, 1943
  - "The Hungarian Spirit"
  - "Identification," excerpt from letter,1955
  - Pittsfield High School, Pittsfield, Mass., "We Can Be Individuals," 1950
  - "The History of the Awakening of Insight", (2 folders)
  - "Interpersonal Relationships, Communication and Psychodynamics," 1951, (4 folders)
  - Jacobson, Edith, "Theory of Affects," 1951
  - "Cognition: Styles, Controls and Cognitive Attitudes," 1956
  - Conversation with George Klein, 9 Feb. 1957, (2 folders)
  - Remarks on paper by Robert Jay Lifton, 1956
  - Loewald, Hans, "On the Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalysis," 1956-1957 (Box I:65)
  - "Some Problems of Prevention of Maladjustment," 1951-1954, (4 folders)
  - "Some Social, Cultural and Clinical Aspects of the Prevention of Maladjustment," 1950
  - Metapsychology
    - Address before the New York Psychoanalytic Society, New York, N.Y., 1958
    - Correspondence with Merton Max Gill, 1954
  - "A Reassessment of the Concept of Metapsychological Explanation," 1954
    - Drafts, (4 folders)
    - Notes, 1955, (6 folders) (Box I:66)
  - Scientific Methodology of Psychoanalysis, 1944-1948, (7 folders)
  - Mittelmann, Béla, memoriam (Box I:67)
  - "Multiple Personality," 1942
  - "On Personality Testing," 1947
  - Piaget, Jean, "Play, Dreams and Imitation in Childhood"
  - "Psychoanalysis as a Psychology"
  - Washburn University, Topeka, Kans., lectures on clinical psychology, 1943
  - "Present Professional Status of the Clinical Psychologist"
  - "To What End Psychology", (12 folders); (1 folder) (Box I:68)
  - Renneker, Richard E., paper
  - "Reaction Time and Succession in the Rorschach Ink-Blot Test"
  - Rorschach testing, 1937
  - "Psychiatric Implications of Rorschach Studies With Metrazol and Sodium Amytal"
  - "Rorschach Ink-Blot Test and General Psychology"
  - "Superego," 1958, (3 folders)
  - "On the Organization of Thought-Processes," Philadelphia, Pa., 1956
  - "Time," fragments of a paper
  - "Time Experience," circa 1947-1948
  - "A Review and Preliminary Remarks on the Problems of the Psychology of Research", (2 folders) (Box I:69)
  - Research assistant, pre-1956
  - Letters to Shmuel Golan on the history of psychology, 1956-1957
  - "The Theory of Affects and Some Nosological Problems," 1951
  - "Notes on Anti-Semitism"
  - "The Autonomy of the Ego," 1950-1957, (6 folders)
  - "The Bearing of the Concepts Autonomy and Activity-Passivity on Therapy," 1956
  - Chicago, Ill., conference, 1952
  - Notes from a conference on cognition, Boulder, Colo. 1955
  - "States of Consciousness," 1950-1951, (2 folders)
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Cognition and Consciousness," 1956
  - "Theory of Creative Activity," 1951
  - "Creativity," 1951
  - "Interpretation of Dreams," 1949-1959, (7 folders)
  - "Early Stages of Ego Development," 1954 (Box I:70)
  - Ego psychology, various outlines and lectures
    - 1951-1956, (12 folders)
    - 1956-1958, (5 folders) (Box I:71)
  - "Emotion," 1948-1950
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Emotions," 1951
  - Suggested references for an unidentified paper of Erik Erikson's
  - "Problems of Etiology and Nosology"
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory," 1954
  - "The Problem of Autonomy," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Action and Structure Development," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Thinking," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Affect," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of Consciousness," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Theory of The Ego," 1954
  - "The Psychoanalytic Approach to Communication," 1954
  - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., outlines of lectures, 1954
  - Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Jerusalem, Israel, 1953
  - Lecture to patients, "Psychology of Imagination Interpersonal Relations and Psychodynamics," 1951
  - "A Psychologist Visiting Israel," 1953
  - "Theory and Investigation of Memory and Learning Reconsidered," 1953
  - Lecture trips, 1954-1956, (4 folders)
  - "A Review of Some Developments in Life Sciences," circa 1951 (Box I:72)
  - "Memory Phenomena in Clinical Observations," 1954
  - Metapsychological papers
    - 1947-1957, (10 folders)
    - 1957-1960, (9 folders) (Box I:73)
  - "Freud and Present-Day Developmental Psychology," working notes, 1949
  - Cognition material
  - Affects, (2 folders)
  - "Dynamics of Personality and Abnormal Behavior," 1950, (7 folders) (Box I:74)
  - Lecture in Philadelphia, Pa., notes on discussion, 1953
  - "Polarization Versus Spectrum"
  - "The Economic Problem of Institutional Psychiatric Practice," brief outline
  - "Hospital Life of Psychiatric Patients," Patient and Staff Organization, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., 1954
  - Patient and Staff Organization, Austen Riggs Center, Stockbridge, Mass., 1954